welcome to the latest rebel wisdom
podcast this is a slightly different
concept
so last week I interviewed Jordan
Peterson again for the second time and I
asked him a few questions about
relationship with the left and he gave a
few answers that I'd never heard before
and we're gonna play some of that in
this podcast and off the back of that we
we've also just come back from America
and we'd recorded this amazing
discussion with some guys from the
California Institute of integral studies
on exactly the same topic what can the
left learn from Jordan Peterson so we
decided to bring out a whole do a few
more interviews on the same subject and
bring out about six or seven interviews
at the same time so if you're watching
this the link to all of those interviews
should be below this in the show notes
and we're gonna play some clips from
those during this during this podcast
because it feels to me like we're trying
with rebel wisdom to really follow the
cultural conversation really kind of
identify where the cultural conversation
is going and it seems to me that for
quite a while on the left in particular
they were kind of waiting for Jordan
Peterson to go away
like anyone who has that kind of
exponential curve usually explodes and
goes away he doesn't seem to be I
actually asked him that question at the
beginning of the interview and his
theory is that this is actually a switch
over from different forms of media from
broadcast media where they get tired of
you and they spit you out to online
media where that narrative no longer
holds which is interesting in itself and
we'll put up that sometime soon I don't
want to get dragged into politics too
much we've basically done lots of stuff
so far about different subjects
spirituality psychedelics our sense is
that by the idea of rebel wisdom is that
what we're seeing is a is a change in
paradigms a change in world views and
we're sort of trying to kind of identify
what that is so
politics is just a subset of this kind
of wider shift that we're seeing going
on and I think for me it's really
important we don't get dragged down into
the political level too much but I think
this is what's been coming up so far so
we're doing one big foray into the
political space as you're saying that it
reminded me of something actually either
Jesse or Matt said from CIA s the CIA s
talk which will be released same time as
this which was around it's much more
interesting to talk about the underlying
symptoms so the underlying structure
than the symptoms and politics for me
feels very much like a symptom of an
underlying issue it's for me in many
ways the least interesting thing to talk
about not least because we know or have
pretty good evidence to suggest that
your own temperament you know how you
balance the big five personality traits
etc has a huge influence in your
politics as as your personal history so
so in a sense while it is important and
interesting I think it's it's almost
it's the tip of the iceberg and and I
personally am also much more interested
in the the rest of the iceberg
another thing as well which is worth
mentioning is that I think we both
started talking maybe just quite
recently a couple weeks ago about is
there a shift happening within the left
now there's a couple of things came out
at the same time there was paper from a
pretty well-known activist here not sure
if you remember of each novel house I
think that's it yeah
mentioning how he'd been putting on
conferences and and they had been taken
over by the kind of what I would call
this the social justice kind of identity
politics fundamentalism and it had you
know this is someone who genuinely cares
about making systems change and he had
started noticing what we're not getting
anywhere it's just you know it's been
taken over
that was interesting and then Obama
criticized the shortcomings of identity
politics ABC put it out and there was a
tweet that something about it's not who
you are that should decide whether you
get to speak yet precisely yeah and and
he used a really nice example of when
Nelson Mandela was in prison and what he
didn't do was kind of polarize into one
thing and get sucked into hate yeah and
I think it's also worth mentioning the
all of these words are kind of labels
like we we talk a lot about integral
theory for example the idea that even
left and we're sort of in a position now
where we're kind of going beyond left or
right and I think that's very true and
it's really important to to say that you
can talk about the word left you can
talk about the word liberal you can talk
about the word progressive they tend
there are personality types that
underpin the sort of the idea of left
and right sort of more one more open
than closed one more ordered than the
other I mean these these are do exist
but there's always a sort of fluidity
when we're talking about this so it's
not that I think especially if you've
been in this sort of space for a while
you kind of maybe even flinch at the
idea of people using the words left and
right because you're kind of well
whipped we're so beyond all of these
labels and it's like well we are but
they are actually pointing to real
temperamental differences and there are
habits of thought on what you might call
the Left which are yeah which are are
shared by most people who would who
would share those kind of personality
characteristics and share those kind of
that kind of worldview so we can use the
word meaningfully I think while holding
it quite lightly at the same time so
without further ado we're going to play
the first clip of the interview Jordan
Peterson Eric Weinstein describe sort of
the cultural moment as a kind of civil
war within the left i I'm I've got a lot
of progressive friends and what I see
happening recently maybe in the last
couple of weeks is a lot of them
starting to grapple with your ideas and
looking at lasting this question what
can the left learn from Jordan Peterson
which is which is a pretty new
development because I saw a lot of kind
of reactivity to it before
how can you personally contribute to
that debate and absolutely no no doubt
about it
no doubt about it what one thing that
I've been doing in my tour repeatedly
when I talk about the first chapter of
my book which is stand up straight with
your shoulders back it's a discussion of
hierarchies and
their eternal nature right because my
claim is is not my claim I think it's
mere fact that organisms that have to
cooperate and compete with other
organisms of their type inevitably
arrange themselves into hierarchies and
that's been going on for so long which
is at least 300 million years that our
nervous systems have adapted to
hierarchies as if they're a permanent
element of being right more permanent
than trees like seriously permanent at
the most fundamental neurochemical the
one that regulates the entire brain
serotonin is acutely sensitive to
hierarchical distinctions and so that's
part of the proposition I laid that
proposition forward was to say whatever
pitfalls hierarchies might produce you
cannot lay them at the feet of the West
patriarchy or capitalism it's like
that's a non-starter you're wrong and
not just a little bit wrong you're so
seriously wrong that if you insist upon
doing that you won't even achieve your
own aims because you're actually not
grappling with the problem the problem
is if hierarchies are a problem which
they are the problem is way more serious
than mere capitalism it's way deeper and
if you're actually interested in
rectifying the constantly the negative
consequences of hierarchies then you're
gonna have to get a lot more
sophisticated than there then your idiot
Marxism so so so part of the elaboration
of that argument is well hierarchies are
inevitable because we have to solve
complex problems and we have to solve
them socially and when you implement a
solution to a complex problem socially
you produce a hierarchy because some
people are better at the implementation
than others so there's a hierarchy of
competence and then there's a hierarchy
of distribution of the Spoils and so and
in both of those hierarchies you get a
disproportionate clumping of resources
at the top and dispossession at the
bottom it's in the nature of hierarchies
so what's the left for the left is to
remind those who are benefiting from
hierarchies that the hierarchy comes at
a cost and the cost is the clumping of
people at the bottom and that that's an
eternal cost and it's not trivial and so
that's what the left should be properly
focused on the Left should be providing
the voice of those who are dispossessed
by hierarchies and the right should be
saying yeah but the damn hierarchies are
necessary and they're not only necessary
but they're also productive then the
left says yes but they tilt towards
tyranny and they can be occupied
inappropriately by people who are
playing games of power fair enough the
right has to take that into account the
hierarchy can rigidity rigidify and is
likely to do that and it can be taken
over by people who are corrupt and
that's likely to happen and so but but
it's okay because the dialogue can work
out the the right can say well yeah we
need the damn hierarchies and they need
to be but wrists and the left can say
yes but they have to be maintained
properly so they don't deteriorate and
degenerate and and I think that's I
think that's ancient wisdom I think the
ancient Egyptians had figured that out
in their symbolic representations so now
when the left goes too far
it does something like say well how
about no hierarchies it's like no how
about not wrong because all that happens
if you flatten one of the things that
happens if you flatten out the hierarchy
is that you can't even organize your
perceptions you can't perceive the world
without looking at the world through a
hierarchy of value and if because you
can't perceive the world unless you make
one thing more important than all the
other things because you don't even know
what to look at and if one thing isn't
more important than all the other things
then you have nothing to aim at if you
have nothing to aim at then you have no
meaning in your life so the left can't
just demolish the hierarchies in the
name of some equality of outcome let's
say because you blow out the future you
leave people aimless and you destroy the
very institutions that allow people to
make competent progress in the world
that's not an acceptable outcome so we
have to we have to agree to live with
the ten
necessity for hierarchies the proclivity
for them to pathologize and the the
necessary voice of the left and speaking
for thee for the dispossessed so and I
mean I've as far as I'm concerned I've
said something approximating that
through my entire career and so the fact
that the left wingers have been
irritated at me is well in some sense
that's an inevitable consequence of me
taking on the radical left wingers but
it's also the refusal by the moderate
left to deal with their internal
problems yeah so the first question I
asked was whether he actually wants to
be part of that conversation like the
conversation with the internal
conversation which as Eric Weinstein
said it feels like what's going on is a
civil war within the left and it's sort
of the mainstream left that's now become
a cult that was the counterculture has
now become the mainstream culture how
does the Left draw boundaries because
the left by by its nature does not like
boundaries so the issue is how does the
Left draw boundaries around internal
boundaries that say well actually you're
trying to hijack the conversation you
have an ideological agenda or whatever
it's like how can you have a generative
dialogue when you can't build boundaries
of people who are not willing to
acknowledge the the things that are
required to have a generative dialogue
that for me is the sort of the best way
of describing what's going on in the
left and I have got the sense with
Jordan Peterson part of this is kind of
optics he's been on Fox News a lot and
he he was also on I think rebel media
very different formal wisdom and the
sense that he because it's such a
polarizing and volatile moment has been
pulled on to one side of the culture
wars but the right has embraced him the
left has kind of rejected him so I think
by definition he's seen on one side more
than the other
personally I don't actually think that
he I don't think he's natural home is
that and I think if people sort of were
able to get past some of their
reactivity to him they'd see that that's
not his natural home yeah yeah I agree
with that I think there's something
around
as you were saying that I was wondering
like could he have been picked up by the
more left-leaning ones and I think
because of that ideological blindness in
the culture within many parts of the
left I think would have been so
difficult for him for them to they
couldn't they can't hold that complexity
I think a few people have written
articles recently about how the right
was able to draw boundaries because of
the horrors of World War two and the
horrors of seeing really what happens
when fascism you know it gets gets the
interposition of power and there's a
weird thing on the left you see it with
Corbin you see it with a lot of the kind
of old-school left and and you know this
the young woman who was on Piers Morgan
and said I'm literally a communist you
know ash Sarkar I think that was just a
few days ago and Douglas Murray wrote a
really good piece actually in spectator
around the insanity of that of like the
right knows how bad it gets when the
right goes extreme the left should know
like and I mean it's clear it's in the
history but we know was a even more
recent and happen over and over again in
many different countries and I think
there's there's that element at play as
well and Jordan P doesn't talks about
that a lot you know he talks about that
the horrors of collective and how the
left how the sort of pathology on the
left is not necessarily one single idea
like on the right it's kind of racial
superiority or right you're no longer in
the conversation on the left it's sort
of it it's a combination maybe three
good values but I think the central one
is that fairness is a good value but if
you make fairness you're kind of primary
axiom it ends up leading to madness and
that's another Eric Weinstein quote he
says that if you build a cosmology on a
narrative of oppression it leads to
madness because as jordan peterson said
in the interview with me if depending on
where you draw the line everyone is an
oppressor and everyone is approached on
some level the the interesting thing as
well for me about the left of this sort
of talk about the mask of compassion
but just this assumption of moral good
on the left and I think Peterson has
been the victim of that this assumption
that all all the moral value is on the
left and on people who think in the same
way as people on the left think and I'm
struck by though there was one piece in
one of his podcasts sorry one of his
lectures where he describes helping one
of his patients as a psychologist with
he he got him a job in a charity folding
letters in fact the guy found it really
really difficult like it's really hard
to do but the narrative that comes
through is that he was with this guy for
like 10 hours and supported him for many
years and it's that's what I find really
difficult when people it's clear that
this is someone who cares deeply about
people has been deeply involved in
people's lives helping people so this
assumption of the left of well he must
be a monster or he must be a fraud all
of this stuff is really it's difficult
to take for anyone who's kind of delved
into his lectures understands the kind
of guy that is yeah not surprising for
me having not really been on the left
since I was maybe 18 and having been
more on the kind of yeah certainly more
towards the right maybe more an artistic
and libertarian at different times but
there is an assumption generally exactly
what you said that all the moral virtues
on the left which is not true when you
actually engage with with thought that
comes from the right especially if you
think about so France Duvall Dutch
biologist has done many experiments
around empathy and animals in in mammals
and pretty conclusively shown that
fairness is something that's built into
us we all have a sense of what's fair
it's so deeply built in that if you get
two dogs do the same trick and give one
of them a treat and not the other one
the other dog will stop doing that trick
and capuchin monkeys men I mean it's
deeply ingrained so to assume that one
side of the political spectrum somehow
has it and the other side don't have
this biologically encoded sense of it is
absurd because everyone cares about
fairness on either side of political
spectrum it's just that they have a
different interpretation of what's fair
and what isn't and this is a really good
time to play a clip for
the CI is debate Jessie Estrin who
lovely guy who works in prisons like
he's been deeply involved in social
justice work for a lot of his life and
yeah I'll play the clip now and you'll
see you'll see what he says I've grown
up and I've been really involved in
social justice issues racial justice
gender justice involved with
philanthropy and activism on a lot of
different levels actually and that's how
I was raised so I've really been in this
space my whole life and this is the
first time I've actually been
encountering are their viewpoints that
would be either more Center more
conservative and I'm actually really
it's feeling really fruitful it's really
refreshing it's really stimulating my
thinking it's hard to see other people
not join me in that and get kind of
weirded out or freaked out by it which
then makes me even more intrigued so
yeah that's a clip from one of the
pieces that we've just put live so it's
a four-way debate that we had with Jesse
Esther no Matthew Siegel after they so
they come from a very sort of liberal
left-leaning college called the
California Institute of integral studies
but were really and Gately put out this
podcast where they started asking what
the left could learn from Jordan
Peterson and what the reactivity on the
left to him said and I love the other
things that we explore in there is why
the quality of the rejection by the left
is so extreme that there must be
something else going on what Jesse says
it's like a psychological complex almost
it's - it's it's out of kilter with with
what's actually going on and whenever
something like that happened you have to
kind of unpack it and try and understand
why people are having such reactivity or
such kind of strong responses to it yeah
I thought that was a really enjoyed
every moment of that conversation really
smart embodied guys it goes that it's
really good flow to the the whole time
exploring the ideas with a mutual
respect and yeah watch it it's good yeah
so one of the things that we looked at
and we thought okay so there is this
there's definitely something happening
where people on the Left are starting to
ask what Jordan Peterson has to offer
and one of those was at
Ronin Harrington put out this film for
his channel alter-ego saying comparing
and contrasting Jordan Peterson and
Russell Brand and in his sort of circles
even kind of validating Jordan Peterson
in st. well he might have something to
offer provoked some kind of reaction in
some of the people that watch the video
but and we had a really great chat where
he agrees with Jordan Peterson where he
disagrees but I think his his central
point about the criticism was really
really good in a way the video was about
Jordan Peterson's thinking but on a more
meta level it was a commentary on a
political culture so we face this
enormous pressure to either love or hate
either public figures or issues or to
endorse them and to reject them and to
be very public in that but people and
issues are really complex and with
someone like Jordan Peterson I can see
lots of as I said in the video profound
contributions and strengths and also
areas for I feel like his thinking is
really off and how can you hold that
complexity in a tribal polarized culture
where you're kind of shut down for
holding it and I think that that maybe
is the new political space that's
opening up as more and more people
willing to go like no I'm not going to
just fall into a binary I'm gonna try
and stay open and hold the complexity so
I think his point that a lot of jordan
peterson admirers like i really don't
like the word fan cuz i think it's a
terrible energy but a lot of jordan
Peterson admirers are really put off by
the tone of the criticism of him it's
not that we don't like people
Krita criticizing Jordan Peters and
Jordans ideas even he himself welcomes
and invites people to criticize his
ideas but it's the tone that comes
through a lot of the time in the media
articles when you hear someone say he's
a fraud or he's a charlatan or any of
this stuff it's like he's clearly not a
fraud or a charlatan
so as soon as you start using that kind
of language in a criticism it's very
difficult to take that criticism
seriously and also it's very there's a
there's such a an arrogance in some of
the critiques that is like I'm thinking
one in particular is like okay you're a
you're a you're a journalist in your
late 20s you've done what exactly that
gives you that the the knowledge the
self-knowledge to be able to kind of
pass judgment on someone who is is
having whether you like him or not this
incredible impact on on people's lives
all around the world but what what is
going on what is going on at a
subconscious level mmm-hmm it reminds me
of I mean there's a couple of answers
that I've heard from a few people which
is that it's like okay that they post an
article it's like that's actually
mischaracterizing his ideas here's the
lectures where he talks about them and
the response is often well I kinda have
time to watch 20 hours of lectures and
my response if if the journalist says
that is like well then don't write about
him you know it's I think that's I'm
just thinking as well of the unrelated
but slightly related the James d'amore
memo that he got fired from Google for
that was a similar thing where I don't
think a lot of the journalists had
actually read the memo so I remember I
read the entire thing and then was like
wow it's not well I've been trying to
read articles and I'm trying to see
where they had parsed these things
together and it just didn't it didn't
gel it's like I hadn't read it and I
think there's that sense as well all
like criticism is needed and so
important that's how the conversation
before but you can't criticize if you
don't engage with the ideas like I don't
I wouldn't criticize Freud because I
know like a little bit about Freud don't
know the body of his work and until I
knew like a pretty decent amount I
wouldn't go out there saying Freud is
bunk so we also recorded a an interview
with Tim lot who is a novelist and
journalist who wrote the first Spectator
article about John Peterson
I think around the same time as I
brought out my documentary really
interesting guy who is described himself
as an old lefty so he's kind of was a
Guardian columnist and was
yeah he talks about kind of the journey
that he's gone on and also the the
danger that he sees in this kind of new
ideology that and the danger of that
impacting art because effectively and he
he puts this really brilliantly it's
like anyone who says I know he's very
suspicious on the idea that I know and
the answer is diversity and equity and
everything needs to be seen through this
prism is ultimately a totalitarian
mindset like there's not it's not that
these values are wrong and this is where
I keep coming back to like the
sophistication and I genuinely would
would like to hear Jordan Peterson
making this point a little bit more
carefully because when he when he starts
railing against diversity and equity and
all these things I can see the kind of
react the reaction that it provokes
whereas like as you said before fairness
is a good value diversity is a good
value if you can imagine like certainly
police officers in their community
should reflect their community will help
them do their jobs better there are
certain jobs certainly where diversity
is a positive value but if you make that
your primary axiom and assume that
that's the only way to see the world and
the only way to kind of organize your
your your being in the world then it
becomes extremely dangerous very quickly
leads to madness we said before so we'll
play a short clip from Tim finally and
fundamentally it's the individual that
matters and how could I think anything
otherwise as a writer if any job is
about the individual voice it's the job
of the novelist you know you know films
are collective projects writing a novel
is the ultimate individual acts the
ultimate individual voice and even that
is coming under pressure now you know
people they have they have I think
they're called something like they're
not called morality readers but their
velocity reader diversity readers know
how editors now who check you know that
you don't have a uni appropriate you
don't have any inappropriate opinions in
your you know even for your characters
that's a really deep sickness as well
and that is that is totalitarian thought
and it's totalitarian thought not in the
government but it's a totalitarian
thought mindset that I see on the March
there are a few things in the interview
with Jordan Peterson I never heard him
say before and the sticking point that I
hear a lot from my sort of more
progressive friends is you all sort of
primary focus is on the individual
yeah well that's that's too bad for them
because the primary focus should be on
you know I can agree with that but what
I the the paradox that they would say
it's like okay focus on the individual
but you have to accept that there are
some situations that are much more
conducive to an individual thriving than
other situations so their focus is on
structural inequality you're focusing on
the individual is there not some
interplay between oh definitely well
obviously because people do have group
identities the question is whether
whether the group or the individual
identity should be paramount and the
left distance the radical leftist answer
is well there is the look it's not me
that's failing to take into account
those two levels of analysis it's the
bloody radical leftist because for them
it's the collective and that's that and
so it's obvious as far as I'm concerned
that people have their individuality and
then behind that they have their they
have their group like multiple group
identities which is also a big problem
but all separately or any of these
situations that make it much more
difficult for people to self actualize
well what I think they'd argue is they
don't hear you talk about that very much
well it isn't first of all it's not
self-evident like I'm not I don't accept
Maslow's hierarchy of needs I don't
think it's necessarily more difficult
for people who are poor to
self-actualize sorry I don't buy that
you because what that would mean think
about what that would mean that would
mean that the rich are morally superior
that's what that means because they have
all the opportunities to self actualize
so obviously if the material conditions
are the prerequisite for
self-actualization then the rich are
morally superior to the poor is that
really an argument we want to make and
then in fact I don't think that that's
even even
vaguely reasonable because one of the
things that does help build character is
privation
now obviously starving to death is an an
excess of privation
so there are limit conditions but the
it's a leftist trope that the provision
of additional material resources will
produce ethically superior human beings
sorry
not true and in fact sometimes quite the
contrary
so-so so I don't I don't I don't buy
that argument in the least I also think
that under most circumstances accepting
those of exceptional privation and even
perhaps under those conditions in most
is in most cases your best bet to move
people forward is to concentrate on the
development of their individual
character and their individual their
individual moral character fine and
because moral character is actually your
moral character is actually the set of
tools that you have to operate
effectively in the world because
otherwise morality would be of no
utility and morality is in some sense
precisely that way which is of maximal
utility and so and and the other
objection that I would throw it at the
radical left is well how do you know
that your your emphasis on collective
existence isn't just an abdication of
your personal responsibility well of
course it's not it's like no no no
seriously here it's not that easy to
adopt personal responsibility maximal
personal responsibility what makes you
think you're not running away from it
you have every reason to you really have
that stellar moral character really
that's that's your self analysis it's
like sorry I don't buy it and I
especially don't buy it when I look at
the consequences of leftist revolutions
because all these people of stellar
moral character when they undertake
their collectivist revolution nothing
comes out of that but absolute bloody
catastrophe so so all the well-meaning
aims aside but he takes the sort of
the individual being paramount and the
collective being secondary which i think
is is ultimately writing has no apology
of that obviously but this sense that
there are certain structural things that
make it more more difficult to live a
good life I mean that seems kind of
undeniable that certain situations are
more conducive to flourishing than
others but then if you expand that to a
sort of more developmental lens which
says okay that the top of the pyramid is
self-actualization the top of the
pyramid is BA becoming truly ourselves
and developing our cell and moral
character and and becoming kind of fully
embody human beings I asked him well
surely there are situations where it's
more easy to do that than others which
is an argument I've heard lots of people
make in this sort of more progressive
circles that I'm familiar with and he
pushed back on that in a way I'd never
really heard before and that was to say
that the idea of like Maslow's hierarchy
of needs so you get the basic needs met
at the top of the pyramid of
self-actualization
he doesn't like very much because
implicit in that is the idea that rich
people must be more moral than poor
people and I'd never heard it framed
that way that way and I think there's
something in that I think there's
something quite profound in that this
equation of more material goods will
produce ethically better people and
that's such a how a strongly held thing
on the left and it's such a key point to
to kind of pull apart that sort of
implicit I think it's not held
explicitly I think it's held in place at
me by a lot of people on the left yeah I
think that was one of the key moments in
that interview for me that that and also
just never thought of it in those terms
at all and it makes me think just if it
makes me think of brexit as well it
makes me think of a lot of the tensions
that are in the society where there is
this kind of assumed there is actually
in many parts of especially the
cosmopolitan city dwelling kind of
liberal of which I'm probably one to be
honest
there is an assumption that all these
idiots out in the countryside are just
you know like Hitler really came from
said deplorable z-- and you know what do
they know they're all racist idiots
there's a complete lack of respect and
lack of attempt at any empathy and so
there's a dissonance within the left
around that that I really think needs to
be I think I said this right after
breakfast as well like I'm a Facebook
post I was like we all who consider
ourselves progressive need to be
progressive and be empathetic and go and
connect and really get to know I mean
yeah that's that's absolutely key and it
never really happened it hasn't maybe it
will yeah
yeah this is the I mean regular viewers
might get bored with the number of times
I say this but it's the shadow of
liberalism it's this idea of this
inclusivity that actually hides a
tribalism and pretty much everyone on
the other side of that debate recognizes
it as a tribalism they feel excluded
they feel rejected they feel judged by
liberals for want of a better word and
the idea this is why I think this is
such a crucial conversation to be had
about how does the left go about
policing its boundaries and go about
healing itself because the left is so
dysfunctional right now and it's up in
is so rejecting so clearly the people it
claims to care about but the idea that
it loves it loves the poor in in
abstract but hates everything they
believe hates patriotism hates all of
the things that give people meaning and
groundedness and all of this stuff and
that's that to me is the most terrifying
thing of what's happened since the
election of Trump and since brexit is
that a lot of the liberal classes that I
know are doubling down on what I think
caused that rejection in the first place
saying oh my god it's worse than we
thought there's so much more racist and
bigoted and everything so much worse
than we thought it's like well perhaps a
little bit less of that rejection of all
the people who voted for for Trump and
brexit maybe a little bit of kind of
self-reflection and understanding that
okay Hillary Clinton and the left you
managed to lose to Donald Trump yeah
that's pretty bad
yeah and that's what was really
interesting about the debate with the
guy that
is they really were on board with that
question they they kind of Matthew
raised as a like we need to look at
ourselves we managed to boost it on the
Trump yeah yeah with absolutely just
just finally in that point you know as
as we're talking about I'm just thinking
my own personal experience linked back
to what Peterson says about moral virtue
and it's absolutely true you know what I
meet someone it's not their beliefs that
rank them in in my mind of how good a
person are they or how how trustworthy
are they and how authentic are they it's
it's empathy empathy is the it's also
the driving force in a lot of it like
this you know integral studies
developmental models
empathy is what's needed to be able to
say yes and to transcend and include and
empathy is what is lacking in a lot of
spheres on the left not everywhere but
in a lot of it like as you were saying
and I think it's spread out fairly
evenly just based purely in my own
experience I think it's spread out
fairly evenly through class and I think
Peterson is probably right about that in
the sense that masses hierarchy of needs
is not the thing that gets you to that
kind of self-actualization it's there's
something else going on you know
yeah and that as well I mean I grew up
within a left very leftist household and
I know this in myself up until kind of
yeah a while after I left home this
sense of like I know the leftist mindset
really well we I don't know whether I'm
on the left anymore so I might say we
but on the Left
people tend to judge each other by views
like very willing to sort of I don't
know if I can like this person because
they think this or they think this well
I know I'm not sure that the same thing
happens quite as much on the right I
think on the right people are far more
willing to judge people by the contents
of their character and by their their
individual yeah by their moral character
whereas on the left there are certain
views that people are sort of testing
out if you are accused of holding those
then you'll be on the pale and that's
and I see this also like even in friends
that I did I have since we started
putting out some content about Jordan
Pederson there's a kind of well I'm not
sure whether I whether I approve of
not sure whether I like you anymore I'm
not sure whether how to behave around
you and that that really that's a that's
a big thing on the left that I'm not
sure is the same on the right yeah I
think from on the right there is a great
respect for individual sovereignty
whereas the left has a great respect for
collective fairness and obviously they
overlap in some ways but that respect
for individual sovereignty also I think
has an impact on it's like well you
think this but that's that's your
business
and I'll stay out of my way you said
have you you know we'll help each other
if we need to but you know and that
there's just pitfalls to that as well
but I think you're just thinking out
loud I wonder if some of it comes from
that the kind of focus on that on the
individual you know talking about sort
of where the left has got blind spots
and where the right has got blind spots
I think it's a good time to introduce
the integral piece because we we've
talked about integral theory quite a lot
it's Ken Wilbur's spiral dynamics model
and the idea of a developmental society
that goes through certain define stages
as they go towards sort of more integral
integral itself is like post ideology
it's a space of there's an ideology at
each at each level and integral is able
to kind of like it it's a flexibility of
mind that's able to see where each of
the the different stages get stuck and
to move beyond it so you know one of the
big conversations in the integral
community has been whether Jordan like
there's been this huge kind of
difficulty of digesting Jordan Pederson
in lots of the integral communities that
I'm aware of
is he an integral thinker is he not an
integral thinker
he seems to incorporate so much into his
worldview but is he a genuinely integral
thinker so we had a great conversation
with Geoff salzman of the daily Evolver
where we asked him to put him on the
spot and said he's Jordan Peterson an
integral thinker and that's what he said
what do you say from your perspective he
is an integral thinker yes I would he is
able to definitely think integrally he
has integral cognition as we would say
his his heart in a way is in
traditionalism in my opinion
in a way that I think keeps him a little
stuck there honestly but I don't care
because what he's doing is he is helping
this whole strata of people who have
never had traditionalism well installed
I think he's right I think for me
Peterson is talking about the value of
listening to people from different
political backgrounds the value of
exchanging ideas this is an integral
viewpoint of being able to say well this
is what this person's believe this is
what they're supposed to believe this is
why this is why but there's a he's able
to sketch that out but I also agree that
there's some probably some kind of
reactivity in the way that he is towards
the left that shows that he's not fully
integral in the way that use in the
world but then I think who is like I
don't I don't know anyone who I would
say is integral all the way down yeah
and Matt if C is Matt Siegal made a
really good point where he said we move
between the different levels like not
integral all day long you know he's like
he can be to use a little bit of the
integral jargon me be green and you can
have a red reaction or amber kind of
thing so it is a constantly flowing
thing I think Saltzman put it really
beautifully with that kind of modernist
heart and integral head and there's
nothing wrong with that as well like he
says it doesn't matter so there is a
place where I think that there's an
implicit value in a lot of what Peterson
is saying that I haven't really heard
him make explicit before and this was my
this is our final clip from the Jordan
Peterson interview in a sense what he is
arguing for is the reintegration of the
sacred and that's what I really vote
that's what I really value about what
he's saying and so if that's the case
and that materialism as a doctrine is a
really it deadens the world seeing
ourselves as merely material parts that
are sort of we happen to be conscious
but we don't understand why is is
obviously deeply kind of opposed to the
religious sense of no there's a deeper
meaning we are here for a reason we are
in some sense
universe revealing itself to itself and
all of this the different ways that we
have understanding our plates and that
somehow we are reflecting the universe
in air in our being all of these deep
theological ideas implicit in his
arguments is the sense that this is a
spiritual crisis this is you and we look
at for example the opioid crisis in
America and the dying off of the white
working class in America to me this is
the evidence of a real spiritual void
this is a real sense of the the the
negative effects of capitalism which can
modify everything turn everything into a
monetary value and most of the the
people that I know or in more
progressive circles are not materialist
they're much more spiritually inspired
and they're much more open to that it's
a sort of Russell Brand's message of
what we're seeing is actually a
reflection of a deeper spiritual crisis
I think that's absolutely true and I
also think that it's implicit in a lot
of what Jordan Peterson is saying but he
doesn't make it explicit so much because
I think he's also got a lot of it's also
true when he defends the system that we
have as the best system that we've ever
created in terms of material wealth it's
by far the best system we've ever
created and if you start critiquing the
system without saying and Wow
look at look at the value in the
technology and the way that more people
than ever before have been lifted out of
poverty and more people have access to
clean water and more all of these things
are true at the same time so I thought
there is a way that he could reframe his
message that I think would connect with
a lot of the people who are currently
rejecting it and this was the final clip
we're gonna play my my sense of a lot of
the progressive people that I know is
that they're not they're sort of from a
new generation they're not generally
materialist that they're sort of very
spiritually aware and I i sense a kind
of implicit message in what you're
saying that I'd never heard made
explicitly that in some sense
materialism is a deadening doctrine I
mean you look at the opioid crisis and
America you look at a lot of these if if
poverty is seen as a more sort of also
also as a sort of spiritual crisis or a
spot that crisis of the soul as much as
anything else
it's mostly that like it's a real lovely
thing if if poverty was caused by lack
of money we could fix it really easily
then but it isn't my point I think is to
say that if if you were framing your
message in that way I think there would
be a lot of people on the left
who'd be receptive to that message sort
of that that actually there is a crisis
of that the crisis of already call it
like worldview has real consequences and
a lot of the poverty we're seeing in the
world is to do with this kind of
materialist worldview that has become
become corrupt or at least kind of
stripped all of the meaning and purpose
out of the world point well right well I
mean I don't believe that material is a
materialist hedonism is a sufficient
solution now it's a bit more complicated
than that because I do think that
functional democratic systems are
actually pretty good at reasonable
hedonism like I'm pretty happy that our
system produces a variety of toothpastes
and a variety of toilet papers and a
variety of sanitary napkins all of these
things that that are basically oriented
towards what would you call them
individual creature comforts there's
something about that that's really
merciful and properly egalitarian and so
a certain degree of material hedonism is
a good thing right because it's nice
that people can have their basic needs
taken care of in a dignified manner but
as a as a ultimate solution to the
problems of life it's insufficient which
is again why I don't really like Abraham
Maslow's hierarchy of needs no it isn't
it isn't a progression up the moral
chain because of the provision of
additional material resources doesn't
work that way that doesn't mean that you
don't want to you want to set up a
situation where as many people as
possible are absent the terrible
structures of privation but we are doing
that quite rapidly thank God so so I
think we're the leftists are less
happy with what I'm doing is the case
that I'm making that the meaning that
transcends mere materialism is to be
found in the adoption of individual
responsibilities because I wouldn't say
that that's a core message certainly not
of the radical left it's not that at all
because generally they construe the
individual as either the oppressor or
the suffering oppressed but not as the
active agent as either of those active
agents the problem with the oppressor or
oppressed narrative is even though
there's an element of truth to it each
of us can be subdivided into so many
group identities that there's at least
one dimension along which we're all
oppressors and that's actually when I've
been looking at what happened in the
aftermath of the Russian Revolution that
was the bloody error so to speak because
you could take virtually any individual
and you could find out it's like if
there's one dimension of your identity
that makes you an oppressor that trumps
all the elements of your identity where
you're a victim and the problem with
that is there is one element of your
identity where you're an oppressor and
so that's sufficient justification to
throw you in with the Predators
and do whatever is necessary to dispense
with you and that is exactly what
happened in the aftermath well not only
of the Russian Revolution but all of
these radical leftist revolutions it's
like well if you're a socialist while
you're not sufficiently pure from a
doctrinaire perspective and if you're a
student well then you're part of the
emerging burgeois class and if your
parents were reasonably what would you
say efficient farmers then you're part
of the kulaks and like it just went on
and on and on and on there wasn't
anybody who escaped from the from being
tarred with the brush of oppressor and
that's because that is because each of
us are in fact oppressors and oppressed
every single person shares both of those
things in common
so the other question I aware of his
blind spots so I spoke to Lena Anderson
who's an author and also deeply involved
in this question about what does a
developmental
you look like and she said something
that I that I've we kind of touched on
this in our podcast where we did a sort
of constructive critique of Jordan
Peterson which is is there a kind of
theological incompleteness like he he's
bringing back he's speaking to the sort
of masculine power of the the culture
and in a real way
saying these there are these sort of
very valuable hierarchies of competence
there is a great story of responsibility
going back generations
her her thought was that he he stops
with the kind of judeo-christian
Abrahamic tradition and doesn't go
further to the sort of the mother cults
and the the sort of things that
sustained us when we were in
hunter-gatherer societies I've got it
I've got some sympathy with with that
and I'd love to ask him about it because
this sense that and this is I think
where his idea of archetypes as timeless
things that's where I start to diverge I
think because if they're not timeless if
they've evolved then potentially what we
are experiencing at the moment is a
shift in these archetypal patterns
because we're moving from the archetypal
pattern of for example male and female
roles based on the history of
Agriculture the history of the value
that males greater physical strength put
on them as protectors and all of this to
some to a time when that's the less
important so is there is there an
archetypal shift going on and before
that there was hunter-gather Stone Age
so join me Peterson completely misses
the animism of the hunter-gatherers and
the mother earth goddess of the early
farmers yeah it's a good question I mean
another way to look at that question is
so he is talking about I agree with with
that reading you know because especially
with the very psychedelic background
enquiring into the nature of like the
Divine Feminine and
what place I has in society in the
history of it and you know how it's been
present in many cultures like Minoan
Crete etc I mean there's a whole huge
topic that is I think that's a really
core important point
what Peterson is bringing to it so is
this revival of you could say the
revival of the divine masculine
archetype in a lot of ways so the
question is I think both need to be
revived personally archetype early you
need the divine masculine and you need
the divine feminine because right now we
we kind of you have the devouring mother
and you have the kind of I mean a lot of
not in their full power male archetypes
as well so which has it's something like
it has to happen at the same time he's
bringing one piece of it but I think
it's a fair critique to say to at least
get them to contextualize that to say
don't you know to inquire into that
question or the archetypes changing does
that need to doesn't need to be happen
at the same time or for some reason that
they need to be a revival of the divine
masculine archetype and then the divine
feminine archetype afterwards or
whatever it might be open question I
think it's a good one there so yeah this
is a trial
we've just overloaded people with
content putting up six things at the
same time seeing how it goes I mean it's
the idea is to try and start a
conversation the idea to try and build a
community and the idea is to try and
create a space where we can have these
conversations in a way that they become
generative they become open they become
constructive rather than getting dragged
into the polarization that we see in an
awful lot of that especially in the
social media space yeah yeah I think
that's it's really key focus in rebel
wisdom right now is how do we yeah have
a two-way conversation a generative
conversation where everyone's adding to
it and we collectively all of us get to
new places and you know explore new
different thoughts there's only two of
us there's 22,000 I think other people
so we've created a discord so the link
to the discord will be under the
obviously the the conversations in the
comments are really valuable as well
it's just a discord discord is a chat
program it's a kind of chat platform
it's really easy to use if you click the
link it'll take you through that kind of
setting up an account and the reason
we've done that taking it on to a
different platform is so that we can
have specific moderated conversations
people who are really engaged can become
moderators we can split out different
types of chat there could be a general
chat there can be a Jordan Peterson left
chat whatever whatever it might be but I
think it's it's important to have it
somewhere outside in its own space so it
can become a community its own right as
well great and yeah get involved go onto
the discord leave your comments and if
you enjoy the content that we're putting
out please do consider sponsoring us on
patreon
we'll also put the link below this in
the show notes so thank you very much
you